[dramatic music]
[Duchovny] Tonight
on "Secrets Declassified"...
government sites so surprising
or dangerous
that they're kept
from the public--
from a luxury resort hiding
a government doomsday bunker...
- If a bomb drops
on the golf course.
anyone behind the blast doors
would be okay.
- To an explosive factory
where every shift
is life or death...
[Martin] I can't imagine
something more stressful
than trying to disassemble
a thermonuclear warhead.
- And even a fake country
in Virginia
that's really
a CIA training camp.
- When you cross the border
into this fake world.
it's Disney World for adults.
- These are the astonishing
and sometimes terrible places
built by governments and
the people who work for them.
It's time to bring them
to light.
♪ ♪
In West Virginia.
there's a luxury hotel
for the rich and famous
that boasts
over 700 guest rooms.
exclusive restaurants.
an 18-hole golf course.
and a secret underground bunker
primed for Armageddon.
♪ ♪
[Hakeem] Nuclear anxiety
is peaking in the 1950s...
and the U.S. president
is concerned
about the safety
of the government
in the case
of a nuclear attack.
The government
has commissioned
these bomb-proof havens
for the president
and his cabinet.
[Duchovny]
Now they want a bunker
for members of Congress--
somewhere big enough
to house over
1.000 government officials
and discreet enough
to keep it secret.
The answer--
a five-star hotel.
[Hakeem] The Greenbrier
is a luxury resort
in White Sulphur Springs.
West Virginia.
This place is a slice
of old-school luxury.
where the rich and powerful
come to do business and relax.
You can find presidents
or celebrities
sipping drinks at the bar.
[Duchovny] It sounds
like the perfect place
to see out World War III.
- It's far enough
from Washington. D.C..
that hopefully
it could escape the effects
of a direct nuclear attack
on the capital city
but also close enough
that people would be able
to escape to it in time.
[Duchovny]
It's shielded by mountains
for extra protection.
- Perhaps what swings it.
literally.
is the hotel's
golfing facilities.
Eisenhower is a regular
on the Greenbrier course.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny] The government
discreetly approaches
the hotel
for their assistance.
and the management
at the Greenbrier
are happy to oblige.
The only problem
is keeping it a secret.
- An immense
construction project
on the grounds
of the Greenbrier
is sure to get
the VIP guests gossiping.
So the bunker needs
a cover story.
[Duchovny] The Greenbrier
gets a brand-new extension--
the West Virginia Wing.
Underneath...
a vast doomsday bunker
unlike any other
begins to take shape.
[Hakeem] The bunker underneath
the Greenbrier Hotel
hosts 153 rooms
spread out
over 112.000 square feet.
There are two chambers
for the House and the Senate.
and there is this vast hall
for joint sessions.
It's essentially
a giant underground capitol
for the government
to continue functioning
in the event of a nuclear war.
- Beyond these chambers
are the facilities you'd expect
in a top-of-the-range
government survival bunker--
high-pressure shower
to rinse off nuclear fallout.
over 1.000 beds
for congressmen and women.
a hospital. a cafeteria.
and a small arsenal
of handguns.
[Duchovny] Perhaps
the most impressive features
are two enormous blast doors
to seal Congress inside.
- Each door is 19 inches thick.
weighs 28 tons.
and they're strong enough
to withstand a nuclear blast
from only 2.000 feet away.
- If a bomb drops
on the eighth hole
of the golf course.
anyone behind the blast doors
will be okay.
- And these doors are hidden
behind a false wall
in the exhibition hall
just inches away
from where guests
are mingling.
- For 30 years.
the false wall stands firm.
and the bunker
remains secret...
until 1992. when rumors
finally begin to leak out.
♪ ♪
[Jesse] Ted Gup
is a investigative reporter
for "The Washington Post."
and an anonymous source
tips him off
that the Greenbrier resort
might not be all that it seems.
[Duchovny] Gup speaks
to former employees.
who confirm
that something mysterious
is hidden beneath
the West Virginia Wing.
But for a genuine scoop.
Gup needs hard evidence.
- So he decides to go stay
at the Greenbrier himself
to see if he can get
that final bit of proof.
[O'Keefe]
When Gup meets the manager.
he goes straight to the point.
He asks. "Is there a government
nuclear fallout shelter
under the hotel?"
Well. the manager
immediately denies this.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny] Gup doesn't get
the answers he's hoping for.
but he's determined
not to leave the Greenbrier
without his story.
- Gup visits the office
of a maintenance company
called Forsyth Associates.
who are supposedly in charge
of maintaining
the Greenbrier TVs.
When he gets to the offices.
he sees something strange.
[Hakeem] He sees a wall
covered with books
on nuclear war and Armageddon.
You don't need that
if you're building TV antennas.
- When he digs deeper.
he finds out
that many of the people
who work at Forsyth Associates
are former U.S. military
cryptographers
and radio specialists.
- Turns out. Forsyth Associates
is just a front company.
Their real job is maintaining
the communications
for the bunker.
[Duchovny]
"The Washington Post"
runs Gup's story
on May 31. 1992.
♪ ♪
And the Greenbrier's secret
is finally unearthed.
Within days.
the government goes public
about the Greenbrier bunker...
and announces
its deactivation.
- Today the bunker
is a tourist attraction.
For about $50.
you can go tour the halls
where the American government
might have been reborn
after Armageddon.
♪ ♪
- A luxury hotel
might be the perfect place
to hide a government bunker.
but in the 1950s. the CIA has
to hide something much bigger--
a vast college campus set up
to train the next generation
of super spies.
♪ ♪
[Sami]
At the dawn of the Cold War.
the CIA realizes
that this is a conflict
that's not going to be fought
by traditional soldiers
with bullets and bombs
but by covert agents
stealing secrets
from under the enemy's nose.
When it comes
to training spies. though.
the Americans
are on their back foot
compared to their rivals
at the KGB.
[Andrew] The KGB has
a decades-old infrastructure
for training spies.
and CIA is relatively new
to the game.
So they realize that
if they're going to keep up
with their KGB counterparts.
they have to step up big.
[Hakeem] The spy-craft skills
that could save your life
and maybe even your country
isn't something that's taught
in any college or university.
The CIA brass realize
that their agents
need training to prepare them
for the real world--
what they're gonna face
out there in the field.
So. in secret. they set up
a new espionage university.
[Duchovny] The first step
is finding the right place
for a campus.
- They need a very large place.
someplace secluded.
someplace cut off.
but someplace large enough
with infrastructure enough
to simulate the activities
of a normal city.
[Duchovny]
They find it
at a former naval base
called Camp Peary.
- It stretches
for 9.000 acres--
more than half the size
of Manhattan.
♪ ♪
[Sami]
To the outside world.
Camp Peary remains
a regular naval base.
But behind its fences.
the site is transformed
into an elite proving ground
for spies.
- Trainees refer to it
as "The Farm."
And generations of spies
are secretly schooled here.
right up to the present day.
♪ ♪
Training begins
when students leave
CIA Headquarters in Langley
on a blacked-out bus.
- The men and women
chosen for this
are among the most elite.
They've gone
through rigorous testing--
psychological testing.
physical testing--
to prove that they are truly
the best of the best.
[Hakeem] When a CIA trainee
arrives at The Farm.
they leave their real identity
at the door.
They're given a new cover story
that they must maintain
throughout the training.
[Andrew] They are leaving
the real world
to go into a fake world.
a fake microstate
that simulates life
in a foreign country.
And it's
in this simulated country
that their
undercover training begins.
- The whole location
of the Farm is one giant set.
There's a town square.
a shady downtown neighborhood.
suburbs.
and then the countryside.
Everyone on the site.
from visiting diplomats
to the local café owner.
is a veteran CIA operative
playing a role.
There's even
a cable news channel
reporting on the region's
fictional politics.
- The Farm really is
Disney World for adults.
[thunder rumbles]
[Duchovny]
In this college.
lessons aren't learned
in the classroom
but on the streets
of its fake town.
- The foundation
of undercover work
is being able to recruit
and handle
foreign intelligence sources.
You're looking for people
who have access to secrets.
♪ ♪
- The whole time.
they're playing cat and mouse
with their rivals and enemies--
other students and operatives
who are trying
to catch them out.
[Duchovny]
Outfoxing the enemy
calls for some of the more
advanced maneuvers
that a wannabe James Bond
must learn.
- You're trained how to flip
a car during a car chase.
how to get in a firefight
and not shoot unarmed.
innocent civilians.
how to parachute
out of aircraft
and survive in the woods
on. you know. no food.
You learn
all the kind of things
that you would see
in a spy movie.
[Duchovny]
The new recruits are pushed
to the edge of their wits.
- After six months
of intense blood. sweat.
tears. stress. strain. anxiety.
this siren blares out...
[siren blaring]
And signals
that the simulation is over.
and any trainees that are left
have made the cut.
[Duchovny] The government
has never officially admitted
it exists at all.
Graduates of the Farm
rarely go on the record
about their experience...
until 2019.
- Former CIA intelligence
officer Amaryllis Fox
actually wrote
about all of her experiences
at the Farm in her book.
"Life Undercover."
♪ ♪
The Farm is truly a journey
that's inspiring
and pleasurable.
more than it is something
that's scary and terrifying.
The scary and terrifying part
is when you have to use
those skills in the real world.
- As the Blitz hits London.
Winston Churchill
needs a bomb-proof shelter
where he can lead his troops
in secret.
It's got 70 rooms. 500 staff.
and the strangest thing
about it--
a private line to the president
inside his restroom.
[dramatic music]
- By 1938. British government
know that war with Germany
is on the horizon.
And this war is going to be
unlike anything
in human history.
For starters. the Germans
have the aerial capability
to rain bombs over
Britain's towns and cities
on an apocalyptic scale.
[Duchovny] To stand any chance
of winning the war.
the British government
needs an emergency hideout.
and the safest place
is underground.
[James] Halfway between
the prime minister's residence
in Downing Street
and the British Parliament
sits the Treasury.
Here. they have a vast basement
ten feet below the ground.
which is used
to store thousands
of Treasury documents.
[Duchovny]
A top secret makeover begins.
- This underground space
beneath the Treasury
is divided
into 70 hyper-secure rooms.
Now. this included everything
from the cabinet office.
offices for secretaries
and switchboard operators.
and a dedicated bedroom
for the prime minister himself.
[Duchovny] The war rooms are
kept on standby for a year...
[air raid siren blaring]
Until London comes
under attack
and Winston Churchill takes
his cabinet underground.
♪ ♪
- On September 7. 1940.
the Luftwaffe drop
1.000 bombs over the capital...
♪ ♪
Killing 430 civilians
and injuring 1.600 people.
It's called Black Saturday.
♪ ♪
Black Saturday
is only the beginning.
57 consecutive days
of attacks followed.
testing the resilience
of both London
and its leadership
as never before.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
Despite the hammerings.
the war rooms
and Churchill survive.
So the Germans
turn up the heat.
- By late 1940. the Germans
are using parachute mines.
And these weapons descend
under an open parachute.
and they're fused such
that they will explode
at rooftop level.
and they'll create a pattern
of destruction
that's 300 feet in diameter.
They can flatten
an entire city block.
If a weapon like this
were to explode
over the cabinet war rooms.
it could bury
the prime minister
and the entire war cabinet
in one shot.
That's a risk
that simply cannot be taken.
[Duchovny] The underground
compound is reinforced
with a massive concrete roof.
referred to as "The Slab."
- That means
that the cabinet war rooms
can sustain a direct hit
from a 500-pound bomb.
[Sami]
During the renovation.
Churchill requests
the expansion
of the complex itself.
It triples in size.
making room for 500 personnel
working underground 24-7.
[Duchovny] Such a bustling
underground workspace brings
one particular problem...
[telephone rings]
That Churchill hates
above all others.
- Churchill
is notoriously sensitive
to excess noise.
So 500 people working
in a busy. claustrophobic.
and echoey
underground environment
can cause quite a ruckus.
- To make the boss happy.
several things
are put in place.
One of them is phones
that don't ring
but instead light up
whenever someone is calling.
They also import
noiseless typewriters
from the United States
to mitigate all the noise
that will be created
inside
this underground bunker.
- The expansion
of the cabinet war rooms
brings a new problem.
With so many people
coming in and out.
Churchill fears
classified talks
with the U.S. president
may be compromised
by spies working
for the other side.
[Sami] He needs a secure line
of communication
with Franklin D. Roosevelt.
so he figures.
where's the one place
I'm not gonna be interrupted
or eavesdropped on?
The bathroom.
Churchill has
a new private toilet installed
for his personal use.
and inside is actually a phone
that connects
to an encrypted line
direct to the Pentagon
in Washington.
So any spy will just assume
that the prime minister
is taking a bathroom break.
when. in reality.
he's actually
masterminding victory.
It kind of goes
back to the old adage of.
your best ideas happen
when you're on the toilet.
Perfect example.
[Duchovny] The cabinet war
rooms remain the beating heart
of Britain's war effort
for almost six years.
Then two days
after Japan's surrender.
on August 16. 1945.
the war rooms and its secrets
are locked for good.
For 40 years.
it lays beneath London.
untouched and forgotten.
Then in 1984...
♪ ♪
The bunker's secrets
are finally revealed
when the Imperial War Museum
opens its doors to the public.
♪ ♪
- Everything is restored
to its original state.
frozen at the precise moment
when the Allies won the war.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
After World War II.
the United States
engages in a race
to stockpile the largest
arsenal of nuclear weapons.
Building the most destructive
warheads on Earth
requires a new kind
of top secret factory.
a place so dangerous. it comes
with a chilling fail-safe.
One wrong move.
and it self-destructs.
♪ ♪
- By the early 1950s.
we're in the beginnings
of the Cold War.
and both the Americans
and the Soviets have the bomb.
So. in order
to regain nuclear superiority.
the U.S. goes all-in
on maximizing production.
The attitude from American
military leaders is this--
if we can't have
the only nuclear weapons.
then we have to have the most.
[Duchovny] A few hundred
warheads won't cut it.
The U.S. wants thousands.
- You're creating
these things in volume.
in a factory packed full
of volatile materials.
One false move. and you'll have
a nuclear fireball
on home soil.
[Duchovny]
A site this hazardous
needs to be remote. secure.
and secret.
- The Atomic Energy Commission.
or the AEC.
begins scouting
for suitable sites.
One facility
that ticks all the boxes
is an old World War II
munitions plant
in the Texas Panhandle.
25 miles from Amarillo.
It's called Pantex.
During the war. thousands
of workers. mostly women.
packed munitions
and shells here.
but now the factory is closed.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
The AEC spends $25 million
renovating the old factory.
and in 1951.
the U.S. has itself
a brand-new
nuclear-weapons facility.
Workers at Pantex quietly
and efficiently assemble
the world's
most lethal product--
while trying not
to blow themselves up.
- Workers assembling
the warheads
must perform what's called
the mating process--
when the explosives
and the nuclear materials
are brought together
inside the warhead.
[Martin]
If there's one accident...
it's going to set off
a chain reaction
that will produce
a nuclear explosion.
- A single second
of human error
could wipe out a large portion
of the Texas Panhandle.
[Duchovny] To avoid
this nightmare scenario.
Pantex builds six new bunkers
for assembling these warheads.
called Gravel Gerties.
[Hakeem]
Each Gravel Gertie
is a steel-reinforced
concrete lab.
where the technicians work.
and above them is what amounts
to a mountain of gravel
held in place by steel cables.
Inside the lab. three workers
assemble the nuke.
And this process
is so sensitive
that one of the worker's jobs
is just to read
the instructions step-by-step
as the other two workers
carry out their directions.
[Duchovny] One false move
from a tired technician.
and the whole facility
goes up.
Hence.
the merciless fail-safe.
- If there's
an accidental detonation.
the explosion will snap
the steel cables
supporting the roof.
The entire chamber
is then buried
under thousands
of tons of gravel.
The design traps
the radioactive material.
reducing fallout by 90%.
However. it also entombs
the three workers
who triggered the explosion.
It's a literal death trap.
[Duchovny] The possibility
that each shift
could be their last
hangs over the heads
of the Pantex workforce.
And yet
production rates rocket.
- Pantex is producing 2.000
nuclear warheads a year.
The U.S. arsenal
swells to 37.000.
That's enough
to destroy not only the Soviets
but every civilization
on the face of Earth.
[Duchovny]
For four decades.
Pantex fuels
the nuclear stockpile.
until the end of the Cold War
forces a sudden U-turn.
The slowdown
in missile production
makes the world safer.
But for workers at Pantex.
the danger levels skyrocket.
- Nuclear weapons
that were manufactured.
in some cases
decades previously.
have to come
into a manufacturer
for disassembly.
I can't imagine
something more stressful
than trying to disassemble
a thermonuclear warhead.
- Nuclear weapons aren't
designed to be disassembled.
and some of these
have been sitting around
for up to 40 years.
They've degraded.
and some of their explosives
are not as stable
as they once were.
- Now it's turned over
to Pantex and go.
here's the problem--
you solve it.
You take it apart. and try
not to have an explosion.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
It's not just the nukes
that are past
their use-by date.
[Martin] At this time.
Pantex is over 50 years old.
and it's in desperate need
of an upgrade.
but. instead. they're rushing
to complete the materials.
[Duchovny]
The rush is so intense
that in 1996. factory workers
blow the whistle.
♪ ♪
[Hakeem]
"The New York Times"
publishes some astonishing
and disturbing claims
that at Pantex.
the equipment is faulty.
and safety measures
are being ignored.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
For the first time.
the public is alerted
to a nuclear threat
on their own doorstep.
♪ ♪
The site is still
in operation.
with as many as 2.000 warheads
still waiting
to be disassembled.
♪ ♪
- If the Soviets sent assassins
to try and kill you not once
but 22 times.
it makes sense to build
a secret underground hideout.
But that doesn't mean
it can't be comfortable.
This is the story
of how one European dictator
commissions
his own private super bunker
to the tune of $20 billion.
[dramatic music]
- After World War II.
Yugoslavia is led
by a socialist dictator
by the name of Josip Broz.
He is better known
to the world as Tito.
[Duchovny]
Yugoslavia is independent
from both Western Europe
and the Soviet Union.
But this comes at a cost.
Stalin hates Tito
and is out for blood.
- The Soviet leadership
has orchestrated
over 22 assassination attempts
on Tito.
so he must be thinking.
it's only a matter of time
until his time runs out.
[Duchovny]
Tito believes
a Soviet attack on Yugoslavia
is imminent.
which would trigger
a global response.
World War III could kick off
in his backyard.
- Tito begins to prepare
for the worst.
with a near-impossible
solution.
He decides to build
an impenetrable retreat
that has to be strong enough
to withstand a nuclear blast
but big enough
to hold his entire government.
[Duchovny] The only way
to meet Tito's demands
is to tunnel under a mountain.
- Tito's engineers pick a site
near the village of Konjic.
and the reason is
because it's remote
and shielded by the mountains.
Plus. its central location
makes it pretty accessible
for government ministers
who are in a mad rush
to take shelter.
[Duchovny]
The question is.
how do you hollow out
a mountain in secret?
- To maintain
total confidentiality.
Tito enforces extraordinary
security protocols.
- He does not employ locals.
Instead. he brings in
construction workers
from other parts
of the country
who won't be able to recognize
the location.
- As an extra measure.
they travel in blindfolds
or in blacked-out vehicles
to the location.
[Duchovny] The site is
cordoned off from the public.
and an immense
tunneling project begins.
♪ ♪
- Workers are using explosives
to slowly and methodically
burrow within the mountain.
It's brutal and dangerous work.
In fact.
later testimonies claim
that barely
a single shift passes
without someone
getting killed.
[Duchovny] As the deaths
stack up. so does the cost.
Tito pours the equivalent
of $20 billion
into the tunnel.
and meter by meter.
his hidden fortress
takes shape.
- The entrance
to Tito's bunker admits you
to a horseshoe-shaped
200-meter-long tunnel
that's carved
into the mountain.
It has 100 dormitories
that are capable of housing 350
of Yugoslavia's political
and military elite.
In every way. this facility
is designed to provide
for the continuity
of government
in the eventuality
of a nuclear war.
[Duchovny]
The base is fitted out
with the latest Cold War tech.
- It contains
five operational centers
with a cryptography center
and even a fully equipped
hospital operating room.
[Duchovny]
The most iconic gadget
is straight
out of a spy movie--
the red telephone.
which will ring
when nuclear Armageddon
kicks off.
If that happens.
Tito can sit out
the end of the world
in relative luxury.
- The rest of the survivors
will have to slum it.
but Tito gets
a private residence
in the heart of the mountain.
It consists of five rooms.
including an office
and a bedroom.
with the bunker's
only double bed.
[Duchovny] The inside
of the bunker is vast.
but the entrance is hidden
to the outside world
by a stroke of genius.
It's camouflaged
behind the façade
of three
regular-looking houses.
- Tito's impossible dream
is finally completed in 1979--
26 years
after construction began.
[Duchovny] But Tito never gets
to take the grand tour.
He dies in 1980.
The secret bunker
is fully operational.
and the Yugoslav government
keeps it on standby.
Then. 40 years
after construction began.
an incredible order is given--
to blow this thing apart.
♪ ♪
- In the early 1990s.
Yugoslavia.
as it used to be known.
is torn apart
as a result of a civil war.
And Tito's bunker is right
in the middle of the conflict.
For the past 12 years.
the bunker
has been looked after
by one of Tito's
trusted servants--
Colonel Grabovica. who's now
with the Serbian army.
Bosnian troops are advancing
toward the complex.
Colonel Grabovica
is given an order
to demolish the entire
facility with explosives.
[Sami]
This is an agonizing order.
because Grabovica
has spent 12 years
taking care of this complex.
When his unit
plants the explosives
and prepares to leave.
he makes a decision
that could cost him his life
for treason.
He quietly cuts the cables
connected to the explosives.
and he saves Tito's bunker.
[Duchovny]
The underground complex
is taken by Bosnian troops.
who retain it as a secret
military installation
until the end
of the civil war.
In 2011. it's finally
decommissioned.
and the government
opens its doors
as a museum and art space.
Locals get to explore
the secret labyrinth
that's been hiding behind
these houses for 60 years.
- A quiet neighborhood
in Germany
is the last place you'd expect
to find a sinister CIA program.
It's a site that brings
together Soviet spies. LSD.
and a Nazi scientist intent
on mastering mind control.
[dramatic music]
[Martin] During the early
years of the Cold War.
the CIA is more
and more obsessed
with interrogation techniques.
They want to be able
to manipulate the enemy
who falls into our hands.
and then they also
want to figure out ways
to reinforce the will
of our personnel who might fall
into enemy hands.
reinforce their ability
to resist
interrogation techniques
that the enemy
might expose them to.
The only way to figure out
how best to serve
both of those masters
is to conduct
psychological experiments.
[Duchovny] The CIA sets up
a top secret program
to explore methods
of mind control.
It's called Project Bluebird.
- These experiments
can't be conducted
in a regular laboratory.
obviously.
They have to be done
in a classified environment--
a sort of black site
that governments
typically turn a blind eye to.
[Duchovny] So Project Bluebird
is taken out of the U.S..
to battle-scarred
West Germany.
- At this time.
part of Germany is still
under American occupation
after World War II.
when the U.S. military
have a site
in a quiet town
just north of Frankfurt.
[Duchovny]
It's called Camp King.
- Camp King has been in use
since World War II.
It was used for imprisoning
and interrogating
Nazi leaders.
[Sasha] Camp King has
the perfect infrastructure
for psychological experiments.
It has secure cells.
housing for staff.
and even a hospital.
[Duchovny]
But its most vital asset--
absolute privacy.
- The locals are used to seeing
the Americans
from Camp King around.
and they don't ask questions
about what
they're doing inside.
[Duchovny] The project needs
a lead scientist.
someone willing to turn
a blind eye
to medical ethics.
- It turns out that the chief
medical doctor at Camp King
has quite the résumé.
Dr. Walter Schreiber
is the former surgeon general
of the German army.
- Walter Schreiber oversaw
horrific medical experiments
at Dachau and Auschwitz.
Under his watch.
concentration camp prisoners
are frozen.
injected with hallucinogens.
and even dissected
to track gangrene--
experiments that end
in slow and painful death.
[Duchovny]
Schreiber was picked up
by U.S. military intelligence
after the war.
Now his skills are put to use
on Project Bluebird.
running Camp King's
experiments in mind control.
- This includes
hallucinogenic drugs.
It includes hypnosis.
The idea is to break
the prisoner from his own mind
and do what the CIA wants.
[Duchovny] The secure facility
has a ready supply
of test subjects.
- Its current inmates
are Soviet defectors.
spies. and refugees--
people who could be considered
expendable.
They could be treated
inhumanely
or die during trials.
and who would know?
- The subjects are described
as experienced
professional-type agents...
suspected of working
for Soviet intelligence.
In one case.
doses of drugs and hypnosis
induce a deep trance.
One spy remains under
for two hours
and then completely forgets
the experience.
[Duchovny] But mastering
mind control proves elusive.
so new instruments
are brought in.
and the facility
expands its operations.
[Sami] They generate
a new set of tests
to try on their subjects.
including exposure to gases.
irradiation by infrared
and ultraviolet light.
pressure chambers.
sonic torture.
and dietary manipulation.
Prisoners are often subjected
to multiple combinations
of these experiments
until they can't take any more.
[monitor flatlines]
- Experiments
at Camp King continue
for the rest of the decade.
when they are quietly drawn
to a close.
But the CIA's obsession
with drugs and hypnosis
is far from over.
[Martin] The experiments
with mind control
inform the administration
of the mother of all Cold War
psychological projects...
♪ ♪
MKUltra.
[Duchovny] In 1993.
the U.S. returns Camp King
to the German government.
who build houses on the site.
Families move in. oblivious
to its gruesome history.
until 2002.
when German researchers
uncover the full details
of Camp King's experiments.
♪ ♪
And the new residents learn
the terrifying truth
about the place
they now call home.
- In the 1940s.
the U.S. sets up a weapons
research lab in Los Alamos
that covers
a sprawling 40 square miles.
But the Soviets--
they go bigger.
75 times bigger.
with a secret weapons facility
3.000 square miles in size.
The question is.
how do you keep that hidden?
[dramatic music]
[Martin]
By the end of World War II.
both the United States
and the Soviet Union
recognize that missiles
will dominate
the future battlefield.
♪ ♪
The Soviets have captured
existing examples
of the German V-2 rocket--
the world's
first ballistic missile.
In addition to that. they have
captured German scientists.
The Soviets want to use
the V-2 rockets
to help them develop
a new missile defense system.
[Duchovny]
The problem is.
they have nowhere
to launch them.
[Greg] They want to test
these bad boys out.
The thing is.
they've got to do this
away from the eyes of the West.
They need something private.
something secure.
[Duchovny]
In May 1946.
Soviet command
signs off the location
of their new facility.
And to ensure total secrecy.
it's in one
of the most isolated stretches
of the country.
- The Soviets choose
a remote location in the south.
in the desert. very close
to the Kazakh border.
at a place
called Kapustin Yar.
It's 600 miles from Moscow and
60 miles from the nearest town.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny]
The extreme isolation
is its major selling point
and biggest problem.
- There's no roads.
no rail. no power.
I mean. there's nothing
out there but empty horizon.
which is perfect for secrecy
and volatile rocket tests.
but it's terrible for
a massive construction project
on an ambitious deadline.
[Greg] It's also
a horrendous place to work.
In the summer.
temperatures can get
well over
100 degrees Fahrenheit.
and in the winter.
it plummets to below freezing.
[Duchovny] But Stalin
wants rockets in the sky
as soon as possible.
so he hands the project
to one
of his finest commanders--
General
Vasily Ivanovich Voznyuk.
- Voznyuk is a man who thrives
on the impossible.
He's legendary
for his iron will
and genius for logistics.
♪ ♪
[Amy] Voznyuk is sent
to this remote site.
and he immediately
gets to work.
He builds a tent city
to house all the workers
and then builds roads
and rail lines
to bring in all
the construction material
they're going to need
to make this base a reality.
[Duchovny]
Voznyuk's team
may be sleeping in tents
on the desert floor.
but in just two months.
they built a launchpad
and a command center.
The new Soviet weapons program
is ready for takeoff.
- In October of 1947.
the secret base at Kapustin Yar
launches
its first-ever rocket--
a refurbished German V-2
that flies
for almost 200 kilometers.
After that.
the Kapustin Yar base
expands rapidly.
A new town is completed.
and it becomes the cradle
of Soviet missile development.
all hidden from Western eyes.
- In the Cold War.
nothing remains secret forever.
Whispers
of a Soviet missile base
send Western governments
scrambling
for photographic evidence.
And in 1959. the British
sneak across the Iron Curtain--
or rather. above it.
♪ ♪
- On December 6. 1959.
a British pilot sets off
towards the Soviet desert.
[Greg]
They're flying an aircraft
that the world
has never seen--the U-2.
[Amy] The U-2 is the pinnacle
in aerial espionage.
It's designed to fly so high
with such
high-resolution cameras
that it should be able
to photograph this new site
while staying
clear out of the way
of any possible
Soviet missiles.
♪ ♪
- He passes
right over Soviet territory.
and he comes back
with the first
high-quality photographs
of Kapustin Yar
to reach the West.
- The photos collected
by the U-2
are absolutely critical.
They tell the Western Allies
exactly what type
of technology
the Soviets have developed.
They tell them exactly what
type of fuel they're using.
they tell them vital things
that they need to know
about Soviet missile technology
and capability.
♪ ♪
[Duchovny] Kapustin Yar
is no longer a secret...
giving the West a vital window
into the Soviet
missile program.
But U.S. surveillance
doesn't slow down progress.
The desert base
continues its operation
and remains the beating heart
of Russian weapons
innovations today.
- There's a facility in Utah
that's bigger
than the Pentagon.
with restricted access.
no windows.
and a secret objective--
reportedly to spy on us all.
[dramatic music]
- In the early 2010s.
deep on the salt flats
of Bluffdale. Utah.
construction begins on
a sprawling 240-acre complex.
Now. this is not
a secret complex.
It can't be a secret.
The place is over 50 times
the size of the U.S. Capitol.
Officially. this complex is
known
as the Intelligence Community
Comprehensive
National Cybersecurity
Initiative Data Center.
Locals just call it
the "Utah Data Center."
- This giant complex is
a National Security Agency site
for cyber defense.
Today surveillance. sabotage.
and even terrorist attacks
can be carried out remotely.
The NSA says
the Utah Data Center
is designed to protect everyday
Americans from cyberattacks.
[Duchovny] The latest
sprawling data facility
barely makes the headlines.
which might be just
what the NSA wants.
until journalists
begin to question
the unprecedented scale
of the site.
- At the heart
of the construction.
four vast data halls
are being built.
each 25.000 square feet.
These will be filled
with cutting-edge computer
servers and hardware
that will devour
65 megawatts of power.
- It will come
with an electricity bill
of $40 million a year.
and keeping those servers
from overheating
requires 1.7 million gallons
of water every day.
[Duchovny]
It's a technological marvel
that you can't see
without top-level clearance.
- Security is fortress level.
with biometric access.
24-7 surveillance.
and barriers that can stop
a 15.000-pound truck
moving at 50 miles per hour.
[Duchovny]
So why all the secrecy?
[Sasha] When journalists
crunch the numbers.
they realize
that the Utah Data Center
can store an unimaginable
amount of data.
Some estimate
it's yottabytes--
a trillion terabytes.
[Duchovny]
To put that into context.
that's the equivalent
of 2 trillion laptops.
- This site could hold
more information
than we ever thought possible
and still have space for more.
[Duchovny]
It begs the question--
what exactly is the NSA going
to store on those servers?
In 2012. journalists
for "The New York Times"
pick up the trail.
when a retired
NSA technical director
named William Binney
steps out of the shadows
and blows the whistle.
[Amy] In the late 90s.
Binney created a program
called ThinThread
that searched everything
on the Internet
for anything
that was potentially harmful.
like terrorist attacks
or any other security attacks.
[Sami] His program
protects the privacy
of innocent civilians
by encrypting anything
that isn't suspicious.
while honing in
on potential bad guys.
- Binney claims
that after 9/11.
the safeguards were removed
and parts of ThinThread
were used
in a sweeping
surveillance program
on all U.S. citizens.
[Duchovny]
In August 2012.
"The New York Times" publishes
Binney's revelations.
♪ ♪
- He contends
that the Utah Data Center
is part of a massive
government effort
to store troves of data
collected on Americans
without warrants
and against the Constitution.
[keys clacking]
[Duchovny]
According to Binney.
every message you send
is recorded. saved.
and stored at places
like the Utah Data Center.
- Allegedly. it's the last part
of the NSA's mission
to own every digital
communication
without oversight
and be accessed
by NSA analysts
all over the country.
[Duchovny] The secret activity
in those immense data halls
remains highly controversial.
To its supporters.
it plays a vital role
in keeping the country safe.
To its detractors.
it's the real-world embodiment
of Big Brother.
♪ ♪
From impenetrable bunkers
to high-security science labs.
governments perform
their most covert activities
behind gates and fences
in top secret sites.
But no door
stays locked forever.
And the truth gets out
in the end.
♪ ♪